in our last session we noted that David
Hume raised serious questions about the
whole experience that we have
of causality and if you recall
I pointed out
that there is a difference according to
Hume between a customary connection
or
and a necessary connection
now his favorite illustration to talk
about this problem is what we call the
pool ball illustration we've used it in
other occasions but we're going to focus
more carefully now on it from hume's
perspective
so we envisioned before us
a simple pool table
and on the table there is a cue ball
and then further down the table there is
an object ball we'll call it the eight
ball if you will now at the end of the
table there's a pocket
now
the pool player wants to shoot the cue
ball into the eight ball and knock the
eight ball in this case into the corner
pocket
I was a series
of things that takes place first of all
you have the pool player he selects his
cue
he puts his chalk on the end of the tip
he takes his position at the end of the
table he sites down his line of sight he
has his cue stick in his hand
he moves his arm
which initiates the stroke
because when he moves his arm
the movement of his arm causes
the cue stick to move in the direction
of the cue ball
and the cue stick now comes and hits the
cue ball
and when it hits the cue ball
what happens
the cue ball starts to move or roll
across the table and we hope if this
man's aim has been good that is in the
direction of the eight ball now
meanwhile the eight balls just sitting
there in the table at rest it's in a
state of inertia it's been just an eight
ball
and the cue ball keeps rolling keeps
rolling and it strikes the eight ball
boom
and as soon as the cue ball strikes the
eight ball what happens the eight ball
starts to move
and it moves in the direction of the
pocket and hopefully will then drop into
the corner pocket and the shot has been
executed according to plan
now Hume is saying we're standing here
watching this we're observing these
things take place
and we see certain actions
follow
upon certain other actions
that we see
contiguous action
or actions of contiguity
and that may be a word we don't use
every day
but if you have a piece of property
where you live let's say you have a
front yard
and your front yard has a border to it
and that's your property line
and right next door to you somebody else
lives
and their property line comes right up
against your property line now these are
two different properties
but we would say
that the first property which we'll call
property a
is contiguous
to
property B that is it is adjacent to it
it is right next door
that's what we mean by contiguity
now going back to our pool ball
illustration
we see actions that are contiguous
actions that take place next to each
other or after one another
and we assume
that we are perceiving
the cause of certain changes
we say oh well what caused the pool ball
to move
well obviously that which caused the
pool ball to move was the Striking of
the cue ball with the cue stick
well what makes the eight ball move
well it's the action of the cue ball
hitting the eight ball which now imparts
Force to the eight ball and the eight
ball starts to move across the table
well why does it drop into the corner
pocket
well once it gets in the right position
all it takes for it to fall into the
corner pocket is gravity to cause it to
fall
because there's nothing there to support
it
do you see the gravity
do you perceive the force
do you have a sensation a visual
sensation of the actual energy that is
being transferred from one ball to the
next at the impact
what is Hume saying here no
you don't perceive the actual cause
taking place
all you see is
a contiguous relationship between events
or again
a customary connection
because it's not that we've only
observed one cue ball in our lives
striking one eight ball in our life but
we've seen it over and over again and
though the shot may be missed from time
to time the basic activity is is the
same that is every time one ball hits
another ball that second ball moves may
not move in the direction you want it to
move or the speed you want it to move
but it moves and we assume a causal
necessary connection
now
the point of all of this is simple
Hume is an empiricist
and he says that all of our knowledge
is based upon what
sense perceptions
Sensations that we have
with the five senses
but we don't have
a perception
or a sensation
of cause itself
all we see
the relative actions of the objects
and we fill in the blanks
I remember when I took my first lesson
at drawing for purposes of Art
and I tried to draw a portrait and I had
a friend of mine who was an artist and
he was trying to give me the some hints
on how to draw portraits by using
different shapes and circles and
triangles and all of that and filling in
the lines and I would try to draw a
portrait of somebody and every line that
I could see with my eye
on the real face of the person whose
portrait I was trying to draw
I would then try to reproduce on the
paper
and my teacher said to me says that's
not how you do it
I said what do you mean I said here's
here's a nose here and there's a line
there and there's a line here and
there's a line here and there's a line
here and there's a line here and there's
a line here and there's a line here a
line here I'm trying to draw this nose
he says no that's not how you do it I
saw how do you do it he said you just
shade this side here in a little bit and
maybe some shading down here
and you leave it alone
I said but that's not a nose he says
yes it is because the human eye
will fill in the details
and he said you're making the mistake of
every amateur trying to reproduce the
thing with every detail and it looks
wooden it looks artificial same thing
with writing wrote a novel and I was in
that novel I was trying to describe this
seedy bar that one of the characters
entered
and I thought now how should I describe
this bar
should I start with the front door and
talk about what kind of woods on the
front door and tell how big the rooms
are give the dimensions like I would to
an architect and tell how many tables
are there how many stools are by the
board you know no you can go on
describing it forever
and I've decided to do it this way the
guy goes in he sits at the bar and he's
sitting there alone and he looks up and
he sees a fan an exhaust fan
by the kitchen
and he notices that the exhaust fan
is so thickly covered with grease that
he wonders
how the blades of the fan
can even turn at all
that's the only description I give of
the bar
can you imagine it
do you have in your mind an idea of what
that bar in its fullness looked like if
he can it's going to look different in
your different minds but you know it's
not an upscale cocktail out
you know it's a ratty joint because of
the fan in other words I highlighted
lighted one detail and let the reader's
imagination
fill in the rest
now what Hume is saying is that we don't
just do that with music
or with art
or with literature
but we do it philosophically
we Supply things with the mind
that we don't perceive
and the big one that we're supplying
here
is causality
so what he does is he shows
that we have no perception of actual
causality
now that raises the question does that
mean then
that once and for all David Hume
has destroyed the very idea of causality
and must we now discard causality as a
law
remember we've talked about this law
that the law of causality says that
every effect must have an antecedent
cause
and at that time I mentioned to you that
that definition of the law of cause and
effect is a formal definition
it is an analytical definition
and it is true by logical necessity
why because the word effect means
something that has been brought about
by something else
and so when I say here here's what
causality means that for every effect
there is an antecedent cause that's the
concept is
analytically true it's like saying two
plus two or four or a triangle has three
sides maybe there aren't any real
triangles out there but in the formal
intellectual rational Arena
it is logically necessary to say of a
triangle that it has three sides
because if it doesn't have three sides
it's not what
a triangle
so if something doesn't have a cause
then it would be improper to call it
an effect
say it again
if something does not have a Cause
then it would be improper to call it an
effect is God an effect
no
why because he doesn't have a cause
there's no antecedent cause for God
all right now because so much science
and so much philosophy and so much
theology rests upon the formal principle
of the law of cause and effect
our reasoning in medicine our diagnostic
programs if you have a stomachache
that's an effect you go to the doctor
and you want to know what what causes my
stomachache is it something I ate or
have I had an invasion of some
micro sub microscopic organism that's
threatening my life
you want to know what's causing your
stomach
but here humans raised questions
about causality itself
or has he
now what has happened since Hume
is that many philosophers and certainly
many students have drawn the conclusion
that what Hume did in his critique of
causality is so cut the rug underneath
causality that he has disproven
causality itself
now there's an ongoing debate as to
whether
Hume thought that's what he was doing I
personally side with those who say that
Hume did not think he was destroying the
law of causality I don't think that was
his point
because he makes some very revealing
statements in his inquiry like well we
don't know what causes one thing to
happen anything
can produce anything that's his
statement
well if he's changing the word cause to
production I'm not going to quibble with
that
what he is being skeptical about is our
ability to perceive the exact cause of a
certain action
now note the difference between saying I
don't know what causes that pool ball to
move
and saying
nothing
is causing the pool ball to move
if I say I don't know what the cause is
I'm being skeptical about my ability to
have a direct and immediate experience
of perceiving the actual cause nothing
new there this was what the debate in
the 17th century was all about as I've
mentioned
it's one thing to be skeptical with
respect to pinpointing the exact cause
it's another thing by going whole hog
and saying there is no cause
if we say there is no cause
for an effect
now we have made a nonsense statement
at the rational level
and our argument would be falsified
so I think Hume has been given way too
much credit or discredit for destroying
causality what he did was destroyed our
certainty about particular individual
causes he's right we don't know that the
grass gets wet because it rained
because we have no direct perception of
that cause
but we do know this
that if the wetness of the grass is in
effect
something
has caused it
and that becomes very important when we
get back later on to Arguments for the
existence of God
because it's one thing for me to say I
didn't perceive creation
that doesn't mean there wasn't one
I may not know how that effect was
brought to pass
but if it is in effect it has to have a
cause that remains absolutely
intellectually necessary but I'll save
that for when we get to con now
and the time that we have left for Hume
I want to mention how his dialogue
concerning natural
uh
religion
has also been a forcible
problem for Christians who argue for
miracles
you can't pick up the Bible and read the
Bible
without encountering claims of
miraculous Deeds
both in the Old Testament and in the New
Testament the New Testament record of
Jesus is the record of a miracle worker
who finally is raised from the dead
as a miraculous thing
now Hume critiques miracles
and in for the sake of time I'm going to
get very simple about this basically
what he is saying is this
that any time there is an allegation or
claim
of a miracle
a natural explanation for the miracle
is much more reasonable
than to believe the miracle claim itself
let me say it again anytime there is an
allegation or claim for a miracle a
natural explanation for the event
is always more reasonable
than
claiming Supernatural intervention
because
of
the ordinary behavior of nature
because of the customary relationships
of nature for example the New Testament
claims that Jesus died and rose again
from the dead
so what the miracle is claiming is
something extraordinary
in the literal sense extra
ordinary why because what is the
ordinary result of death
people who die ordinarily stay dead
and so he looks at this in terms of
empirical analysis and he said we have
not just thousands and not even just
Millions but multi-millions of cases
where people die and they stay dead
so that the customary relationship of
staying deadness following dying
that customary relationship is
astronomical
in terms
of its mathematical occurrence
and so Hume applies what he calls the
probability quotient
to every
particular claim for a miracle
in simple language a probability
quotient is the odds
so here we have a book that tells us
that this man lived and he died and he
came back from the dead what are the
odds
the probability quotient given the
customary relationships of the
contiguous events of death and so on
are astronomical in the probability
quotient that such and such a thing
really never took place
now I have heard apologists for
Christianity use arguments like this
that
the death of Jesus and his resurrected
is reported by people
who
gave their lives
for their conviction that he really rose
from the dead
or you'll hear this argument Jesus was
either
a liar
he was deluded
or he was who he said he was
and then they'll go on and start
eliminating all of the options until he
was the way who he said he was and they
eliminate the you know the idea of how
incredible would be that these people
would claim these Miracles and believe
them at the risk of their life and limb
and die as Martyrs and defense them well
certainly
uh that's an extraordinary thing
to find people with the magnitude of
faith and consistency of life that we
find in the new possible in the New
Testament records
but beloved
which is more extraordinary
that somebody should die for a
conviction
or that somebody should come back from
the dead
which is more regular
that a person who claims to be God
incarnate
is nuts or a liar
or that he really is
if you really want to weigh these things
on the basis of probability quotients
against normalcy these arguments fall
dead by their own weight
now
the problem that the human gets himself
into is that one of his chief critiques
of Miracles is that a miracle cannot
believe be believed because it
postulates a unique event
a unique event that is different from
all these repeated occurrences of
customary relationships
again if it happens 10 billion times
that a person dies then they stay dead
and then all of a sudden somebody claims
to have come back from the dead that
would be a unique event and anything
that claims to be a unique event is out
of here has to be dismissed
as being astronomically improbable
what's wrong with that
well we would isolate that or recognize
it as an ice as a unique event
on the basis of say a hundred million
similar events
that would differ from this one
well how do you get 100 million
similar events
how do you get from one
to 100 million
you have to count
you have to add them up right
so the first guy in the world that lives
and dies and stay dead that's example
number one that's exhibit a
the second guy that dies is the second
one and you do that all the way up to
100 million what's wrong with this
well remember the first guy that died
was a unique event
and so we can't count it
doesn't count
because it's Unique
now the second guy dies
well
what about now it's not unique is it yes
it is because the first one has already
been discounted
so the second death is a new unique
event
so that can't you can't have number two
and following this Lodge you can't have
three four five six seven eight all the
way up to 100 million
what this does simply is rule out of
possibility all events
because all events in a certain sense
are unique well our time is up I'll talk
just a little bit more about this in our
next session as we introduce the most
pivotal character of this whole period
Emmanuel Kant